Good morning everybody.
Wait for a minute and then we'll begin
class.
Just a request. Today's class is
somewhat long. As always, I will be
asking you questions.
Uh, humor me and answer me quickly.
That's
Okay, let's begin.
So,
we're going to continue our series of
lectures on recurrent neural networks.
Specifically, we're going to be looking
at sequence to sequence models. So, what
is a sequencetosequence model? It's a
model where a sequence of inputs goes in
X1 through Xn and a different sequence
Y1 through YM comes out like in speech
recognition speech goes in a word
sequence comes out or machine
translation one word sequence goes in
another one comes out dialogue systems a
user statement goes in and a system
response comes out or question answering
a question goes in an answer comes out
in every case a sequence goes in
outcomes a sequence
And there is no requirement that the
number of in number of symbols in the
input sequence has any direct
relationship to the number of sequ
symbols in the output sequence. There
need not even be synchrony between the
two. So we can identify two kinds of
problems. One where one kind of sequence
to sequence problem where there is some
kind of a synchrony between the input
and the output like in speech
recognition. If speech goes in and a
word sequence comes out, if you reorder
the speech, the word sequence will also
guaranteed reorder the same way. Whereas
you have a different kind of problem
where uh like in machine translation, a
word sequence goes in, a different word
sequence comes out. It is possible to
reorder the input word sequence and
still get the same output word sequence
and have it be right. So there is no
onetoone correspondence between the
inputs and the outputs.
Uh I have examples of machine
translation. I ate an apple translates
to Isha and an upfill gigasen. And I've
marked the uh correspondences. I
corresponds to ish but 8 actually splits
into two harbor and gigasen on the
output side. So there's no one to
correspondence. The output may not even
seem related to the input. Like in a
dialogue system, if you say, "My screen
is blank." And the system comes back
with, "Please check if your computer is
plugged in." There is no one to
correspondence between the two. Yet the
answer is right.
The kind of problem we are currently
looking at is where there is a
correspondence, an alignment between the
input and the output. We using speech
recognition as an example. So here the
input and output sequence happen in the
same order although they may not be time
synchronous. So what this means is that
they're order synchronous. So the output
sequence can be aligned against the
input like in speech recognition. The
input speech can be aligned to the phone
sequence that is being output.
So the problems we saw in this kind of
setup were were twofold. First, how do
we perform inference on such a model?
How to output time asynchronous but
autosynchronous sequences? And the
second was how do we train such models?
This we partially addressed. We show we
showed that we could do something
somewhat reasonable using greedy search.
It's not fully answered. The problem of
inference is something that we will go
back to at the end of today's class. The
one that we are more interested in is
how do we train such models?
So here we saw that if your training
data consisted of inputs and an order
aligned output sequence with the
alignment given then the training was
straightforward. You could just expand
the desired output sequence out to be
times synchronous with the input and
then define a divergence which is the
sum of the individual divergences at
each time. And if you use the callback
library divergence as the divergence at
each time, then the overall divergence
simply became minus of the sum over all
time of the KL divergence at each time.
And the KL divergence at any time we saw
was simply the negative of the log
probability assigned to the target
symbol by the network. Does everybody
remember all of this? Yes. Now,
all of this. Okay, good.
And so here the divergence was minus sum
over all time of the log of the
probability assigned to the correct
symbol in the expanded symbol sequence
at each time. So if you took the
derivative of this divergence with
respect to the output of the network at
any single time, then of course uh
that's simply going to be the derivative
of the log probability assigned to the
target symbol at that time. So that's
going to be a whole bunch of zeros. And
for the target symbol alone, the
derivative is going to have minus1 over
the probability assigned to the symbol.
So this is what we saw in the last
class.
The problem arose when no alignment was
provided. So if only the output symbol
sequence is provided but no timing
information is given. In this case we
saw that one way of doing this was to
guess the alignment.
You would initialize the alignment
somehow, train models with a given
alignment, and then using the train
model, you would realign the symbol
sequence to get a new alignment and
iterate the process until the whole
thing converged.
So that leads us to our very first hole.
Okay, 10 seconds, guys.
All right, let me end this poll.
What are the answers? What's the answer
to the true and true? Right. Bay
training explicitly estimates the
alignment of each training instance and
computes the divergence for the
estimated alignment. It requires the
reestimation of alignments at every
iteration.
And we said there was a problem with
this approach. What was that?
That's correct. So we said there was a
problem on this approach. What was the
problem here? Anybody recall
what was the problem?
anyone.
Okay, let me remind you because this is
heavily dependent on the initial guest
alignment and if it's poor then the
model that you train is not going to be
very good and then the fresh alignments
that you estimate from it are going to
be bad and the entire training can very
quickly fall into a poor local optimum.
So that make sense to everybody?
Okay. And so the alternate solution we
suggested was that we should not commit
to an alignment any single alignment
during any passive training. So this was
the second approach that we briefly
mentioned in the last class. If the
alignment is not provided, one solution
was to guess the alignment. The second
was to consider all possible alignments.
How does that work?
So to understand this we have to go back
and look at how we actually computed the
alignments in the first place.
And the way we did this was if you were
given a symbol sequence. We computed a
reduced probability table by pulling out
the probabilities for all the symbols in
the sequence and arranging them in a
separate table. And then any path
through this table from the top left
corner of the table to the bottom right
corner of the table gave us an alignment
of the compressed symbol sequence to the
input.
And the specific path we chose at any
time was the most likely alignment, the
most probable alignment.
And when you uh uh computed the
divergence using this most probable
alignment that was simply the sum
overall time of minus of the log of the
probabilities
of all the symbols at each step in the
alignment. So everybody remember this?
Yes. Now yes. Whoever just drew the pink
line, could you please erase it? I can't
do this. Right. So the issue with this
is that
this can be way off. The one single
guess alignment can be really poor
especially in the early stages of
training when the model is not yet
anywhere close to convergence
particularly the model is poorly
initialized.
So our solution is to this is to realize
that there isn't just one alignment. If
I look at this graph, there are many
paths through this graph.
Each path represents an alignment. So if
I
rep sort of drew a chart of each of
these alignments on the x-axis
and the probabilities of these
alignments in the y along the y-axis,
we chose the one alignment that had the
highest probability and went with it.
This we saw was somewhat of a problem,
right? Can someone suggest because this
could end up hooking on to a really bad
alignment. So can someone suggest an
alternative solution to this? There are
many alignments within the graph each
which are each with its own probability.
We just chose the largest one. The the
alignment with the largest probability.
Is there an a different solution that
you can think of?
Anyone compute the average over all
possible alignments? Right. You could
sample an alignment randomly that's less
likely to go into according to this
probability distribution that's less
likely to go into a crappy local optimum
or just average across all alignments
which is a more robust technique.
So how do you compute the average across
all possible alignments? Now for any
given alignment the divergence is the
negative of the sum over all time of the
log of the probabilities assigned to the
symbols at each time in the alignment
right
this you remember yes or no
guys
what we want to do is to take the
average so each alignment over here will
have a corresponding log probability of
this kind. The alignment itself has an
overall probability. Remember the
alignments have a probability
distribution. So our ex our average is
going to be the log probability negative
log probability of each alignment
multiplied by the posterior probability
of the alignment itself. that it's the
expected value of the uh negative log
probability of the alignment. But then
okay even if I before I get into the but
then here is my second pole
10 seconds, Guys,
my don't worry about it. 10 seconds. 5
seconds.
All right, let me close this.
Can tell me somebody tell me the answer
to the first question. True or false?
Second one.
Second one's false. Right. The training
without alignment computes the average
divergence over all possible alignments.
Because you're computing the average
over all possible alignments, it follows
that you don't need to actually estim
explicitly estimate an alignment of the
label sequence to the input.
So here we are again. The new divergence
is the expected value of the divergences
overall alignments. It's the expectation
of minus of the sum over all time of the
log of the probability assigned to the
symbols at each time along the
alignment. But then expectation is a
linear operator. So the expectation can
go into the sum. And so the divergence
actually ends up becoming minus of the
sum over all time of the expected log
probability of the uh symbols in the
alignment at time t. So what is this
guy? You're summing over all time at
each time. Each of these nodes in the
graph has a log probability. You're
going to compute the average of the log
probabilities on all across all the
nodes at that time. But it's not just a
regular average. It's a weighted
average. And the weight is this time
term over here. The weight for any node
is going to be the probability that a
randomly chosen alignment will go
through that node.
That make sense? You're summing over all
time
over all time at each time you're
summing over all nodes and over all
nodes you're multiplying the log
probability at the node with the
probability that
a random alignment goes through that
node and of course there's the minus
outside to make it a negative log
probability. Did this did this make
sense?
Right? We are not considering all
equally likely. This term is the weight.
So where does this weight come from?
This is the probability that when you
align the symbol sequence to the input,
the specific symbol s will align to the
tth
time in tth input in the sequence. So we
need to be able to compute this. And
what exactly is this for any given node?
This is the probability
that an alignment will go through this
node.
So this is going to be basically
proportional to the probability total
probability of all paths through the
graph that go through this node. That
make sense to you that this guy it's
proportional. I'll see tell you why it's
proportional and not just equal to all
path the total probability of all paths
that go through the node s at time t in
the graph that make sense to everybody
yes or no
okay all right so what is that that is
going to be the total probability of
this highlighted graph in the picture
did that also make sense it's all paths
that go through this node
So we need to compute this probability.
And how do we compute this probability?
To do that, we're going to decompose the
graph into two subsections. The first is
all paths going up to this node and the
second is all paths starting from the
nodes immediately following this node.
So the probability of the blue blue
graph, the total probability of all
paths going through this node is going
to be the total probability of all paths
in the blue graph times the total
probability of all paths in the red
graph conditioned on the blue graph.
What I mean by condition on the blue
graph is that is the condition that the
alignment of the initial portion of the
input falls within this blue graph. Did
that make sense?
Yes or no? Right? So it's P of the blue
graph times P of red graph given the
blue graph
and this term. So we can write it down
as the probability of product of two
probabilities. The first is the
probability of this blue graph. The
second is the probability of the red
graph which is all paths that come out
of here but not including this guy given
that the initial alignment lies within
the blue graph. Great.
But there's this conditioning, you know,
given that the initial portion lies
within the blue graph. That looks kind
of weird. It turns out we don't have to
worry about it. Why? Because when you
compute the vector of probabilities at
any time using a recurrent neural
network, the recurrence is through the
hidden state, right? So then you compute
a vector of probabilities.
When you compute the alignment, the fact
that this guy aligns to symbol D over
here does not in any way any way
influence the computation of this vector
of probabilities because that is not
going back into the graph. Which symbol
this guy was aligned to at this time
does not influence the computation of
probabilities anywhere over here because
that is coming only through the hidden
state. Did that make sense?
Yes. No. Right. So this portion of the
graph is conditionally independent of
this portion of the graph once the input
has been provided. And so what this
means is that
I don't need to condition the total
probability of the blue portion of the
graph on what happens before it. So the
overall probability of the graph is
simply going to be the total probability
of the red portion of the graph.
which ends at this node at at this times
the probability of the blue portion of
the graph that follows this node. We're
going to call call this first guy the
forward probability alpha tr which is
the alpha for the graph that that
arrives at node at symbol number r at
time t. And the blue portion of the
graph we're going to call the backward
probability bet
which is the probability of or the
portion of the graph that starts
after symbol r at time t. That make
sense over here what we're talking about
over here. Yes or no?
Okay. Can I get a few more yeses? All
right. And so given this now let's see
how we compute this.
I'm going to call this first node, first
term alpha t. It's my forward
probability.
How do I compute it? That's the
probability of this portion of the
graph. It is the total probability of
all paths that start from the source
node and arrive at this sync node which
is the node at symbol r at time t. So is
this notation making sense? alpha tr is
the total probability of all paths that
start from the source node and end at
row r at time t. Okay, how can I compute
that? Now clearly you can see that there
are only way two ways to arrive at this
node over here. This node has two
parents. So any path that comes from
here has to be either a path that went
through the first parent and then trans
transition to this node or a path that
went through the second parent and then
transition through through the node. So
alpha tr is going to be the sum of the
total probability of all paths that
ended at symbol b at time 2 and then
transition to y3 e over here plus the
total probability of all paths that
ended at symbol e at time 2 and then
transition to e at time three. Did this
breakup make sense this guy?
And what is the total probability of all
paths that end over here? What is that?
Anyone?
What is the total probability of all
paths that end over here?
Anybody
one?
So the total probability of all paths
that end over here is alpha let's say 3
E. Correct?
So what is the total probability of all
paths that end over here?
This is going to be alpha 2b. Correct?
What is the total probability of all
paths that end over here?
Anyone
is the total probability of all paths
through this graph. Right? What is that?
Alpha 2 E. That makes sense to everybody
that this is the total probability of
all paths that arrived at symbol r minus
one at time t minus one. This is the
total probability of all paths that has
arrived at symbol r at time t minus one.
And so alpha tr is going to be simply
alpha in this case alpha 3 e is going to
be alpha 2b * y3 e plus alpha 2 e * y3
e. That make sense?
Okay. And so here we are, right? The
total alpha
at 3 is going to be the sum of alpha 2 b
* y 3 + alpha 2 e * y 3 or more
generally it's going to be the sum over
all parents of this node of their alphas
times the probability at the node. Did
this make sense?
to everybody.
Yes. No. Okay. Very good. And so there
we have it, right?
Alpha TR is the sum over all parents of
node tr
of the alpha at the parent times the
node probability itself. This is the
total probability of the entire subgraph
that starts from the source and ends at
the node ti.
And so in our case each node has only
two parents. Node tr has parent tus 1 r
- one and t - 1 r. So alpha tr is alpha
t - 1 r plus alpha t - 1 r - 1 times the
node probability. Correct?
You okay with this?
Okay.
And so here is how our forward algorithm
works.
You're going to initialize and you're
going to start from the very first
column and you're going to compute the
total subat probabilities to all nodes
all all graphs that end on these nodes.
That's going to be just the symbol
probability itself for this first node.
And since these guys are not allowed in
the graph that the alpha for these guys
are all for these guys are all going to
be zero. That make sense to everybody?
Okay. And so then subsequently you go to
the next column. So that those are the
alphas. Then you go to the next column.
For each column you first sum the alphas
for all the parents. This guy of course
has only one parent. So it has only one
alpha. This guy has two parents. So you
sum those two alphas. And then you
multiply that alpha by the node
probability. So the alpha for this guy
is going to be the alpha here * y 1 b.
The alpha over here is going to be this
alpha plus this alpha which just happens
to be 0 * y1 e. Did this make sense?
Right all of it. And so if you just
follow this you're going to find that
the last two nodes also have
zeros for the alphas. Then you go to the
next column and you go down the column.
For each node, you add the alphas for
their parents. And then you multiply
that sum alpha by the node probability
to get the alpha for the node. Once you
compute the alphas for all the nodes in
column 2, you proceed to column 3. And
again, you use the same thing. You go
from the top to the bottom. For each
node, you sum the alphas for all the
parents. And then multiply by the node
probability. and keep going left to
right till you go through the entire
graph.
That make sense to everybody this
algorithm?
Yes or no? Yes. And so once you do this,
you're going to have the alphas for all
the nodes in the graph. Not just the
node you're interested in, but all the
nodes in the graph.
And of course the alpha for this guy is
going to be the total probability of all
paths that started from here and ended
over here. Correct.
This guy
that's simply going to be the
probability that this symbol sequence
can be aligned to the input. So the
alpha at this bottom right node is the
probability of this compressed symbols
sequence across all alignments. Did that
make sense?
That's not going to be one because
remember you can have some other the
input is just being measured and every
symbol sequ you can compute a similar
graph for every possible symbol sequence
and every possible single symbol
sequence will have an alpha.
So this is not going to be one. It's
just the probability of this symbol
sequence, right? So, is everybody with
me so far?
Yes or no?
Okay.
And so, we've computed the alpha for
this node. I'll call it I'm calling it
alpha tr. Let me just replace this up
with alpha tr. and the probability again
in this in this formula again remember
I'm trying to compute the total
probability of the highlighted graph
that goes through this node the forward
pass gave me the alphas for all the
nodes and from that I can get the alpha
for this node so now I need to compute
the second term the total probability of
all the paths that started from this
node but did not include this node and
ended at the sync so it's the total
probability of all paths starting from
here but not including this node and
that ended at this node.
That make sense to everybody what I'm
trying to compute.
Okay. Now, not including this node makes
it a little annoying. So, what I'm going
to do is to also include this node and
compute the total probability of all
paths from here to the destination
including this node. But then once I'm
going going to call that beta hat tr and
then once I compute beta hat tr I will
just divide beta hat by the probability
of the node itself to get the beta which
is just the probability of the graph
without this node. Did this make sense
what I'm doing here
all of you guys? That make sense? Can I
get a few more yeses? Okay, clear.
And so now once you do that we know
exactly how to compute it. The total
probability of all paths from here to
the sync that can now there are this
node has only two children in my
example. So to get from here to the
sync, you can either go from here
to this green node and then have the
total probability of all paths from the
green node to the sync or I can go from
here to the red node and then have the
total probability of all paths from the
red node to the sync. Did this make
sense? This equation over here, this
this what I have in the figure and the
corresponding equation,
right? And what is the total probability
of all paths that go from here to the
sink? What is that?
What is that over here guys?
The total probability of all paths from
here to the sink we said was beta hat
3e. Right? What is the total probability
of all paths that go from here to the
sink?
What is that going to be?
Anyone?
That's beta hat for E, right?
Time for symbol E. Yes or no?
What is the total probability of all
paths that go from here to the sink?
What's it going to be?
That's that's beta hat for F. That's
what we called it, right? The total
probability from any node to the sync is
basically the beta for that node. Beta
hat for that node. So the total
probability for all paths from here to
the sync is the beta hat for this node.
The total probability of all paths from
here to the sync is the beta hat for
this node. So this guy is simply going
to be beta hat for E. This guy is simply
going to be beta hat for F. That make
sense to everybody?
Yes. No. Yes. Okay. And so here you have
it, right? So beta hat 3 e is going to
be the node probability y3 e times beta
hat 4 e plus beta hat 4f.
And now this gives us this backward
algorithm. The beta hat for any node is
the node probability
times the sum of the betas of all the
children of that node. This make sense?
this equation,
right? And I see a few more yeses
because this is about this is about as
complicated as it gets. And so this
gives us a way to compute the betas for
the entire graph. First, you start off
with the beta hat for this bottom right
node, which is simply going to be the
node probability itself. And the beta
hat for these nodes is going to be zero
because the graph cannot end at these
nodes.
So did this initialization make sense to
all of you?
Right? And then subsequently I can take
a step back. So these are the beta hats.
Then I take a step back and I compute
the beta hats for all these nodes. And
the beta hat for each node is going to
be the node probability times the sum of
the beta hats of all the children of
that node. And so I get the beta hat for
all the nodes over here. Then I can take
a step back and then go down these nodes
and compute the beta hats for each of
these nodes. Once again, the beta hat
for any node is the node probability
times the sum of the beta hats for all
the children of that node.
I can I can keep stepping backwards all
the way to the beginning of the graph.
That make sense to everybody?
Yes. No. Yes. Okay.
And so the node probabilities were
computed from the input by the by the
recurrent neural network way back,
right? So we'll get back to that. But
then the uh what we want are the betas
and the betas are computed by just
dividing out the beta hat by the node
probability.
And so we can use this backward
algorithm to compute the beta hats and
subsequently divide the beta hat at each
node by the node probability to get the
betas. Did that make sense to everybody?
Yes or no?
All right. So
and so here you have the entire backward
algorithm. You initialize the beta hats
to be zero here just the node
probability here. Then you work your way
backwards within each column you go down
the nodes and at each node you compute
the beta hat for the node as the node
probability time the sum of times the
sum of the beta hats for its children.
From the beta hat you compute the beta
itself by just dividing it by the node
probability. And so at the end of it now
you have the betas for every one of
these nodes as well. That's the
probability of this blue graph. Right?
So where because at t t minus one I'm
going from 0 to t minus one rather than
0 1 to t David. And so t minus one was
initialized out here.
Right. Okay.
And so once we've done that, we have
computed the betas for every node in the
graph using the these are the backward
probabilities. And so you can replace
this probability of the big blue graph
by the beta which you have computed
using the backward algorithm. And so the
total probability of all paths going
through a particular node is simply
going to be alpha tr times beta tr. It
just so happens that if you look at this
term alpha TR * betr for each of the
nodes in a column, these four won't
necessarily sum to one. Those four are
basically going to sum to the total
probability of all paths from here to
here, which is just the probability of
the symbol sequence itself. But what I
want in my formula is the posterior
probability that if I randomly chose a
path specifically from this graph, what
is the probability that it would go
through this node? And so that must sum
to one for the four nodes. So how can I
convert this guy which doesn't sum to
one when I sum over all four nodes to a
value that actually sums to one. How
would I convert it?
anybody
softmax I just normalize it right so
here it is this is what you got for each
node alpha tr bit time beta tr you sum
that over the column and you divide by
the sum and that's going to give you the
posterior probability of each node uh
when the prob posterior probability that
an alignment of this of the symbol
sequence to the input goes through any
particular note. That make sense to
everybody? This one here
which is this right? And so this guy is
what we will call a gamma
which is the product of alpha and beta.
The gamma for any node is the product of
alpha and beta for the node normalized
by the sum of the alpha beta products
down the column.
And so here we have it. Our our
divergence was the sum over all time
of the sum over all nodes at each time
of the product of the posterior
probability of the node and the log
probability at the node which is simply
the product of the gamma at the node and
the log probability at the node.
We have a formula. This makes sense to
everybody.
It's okay. Beautiful.
And that leads us to our third pole.
Oh, yeah. We'll get to that in a few
minutes.
10 seconds, guys.
All right, let me stop the poll right
here.
What are the answers guys?
Both right. The forward backward
algorithms is used to compute the eight
posterior probability of aligning each
symbol in the compressed sequence to the
input. These are required to compute the
expected divergence across all
alignments of the compressed symbol
sequence to the input. And so here we
are.
Now the divergence was computed off
reduced graph. But what we really need
to compute the uh gradients that are
used in back propagation are the
derivatives of the divergence with
respect to the output of the recurrent
neural network at each time. And at each
time the recurrent neural network
actually computes a probability vector
that includes probabilities for all the
symbols in the vocabulary. Right? So
you remember this? Yes. No.
Right. And now so the derivative of this
divergence
will it have a nonzero value for any
symbol that doesn't occur over here?
Will it?
Yes. No. No. Right. So the derivative of
the divergence with respect to the
output at any time, say this guy, is
going to be a vector which has a bunch
of zeros for for symbols that are not
here. And for the symbols that are over
here, you're going to get the
derivatives of so this is time six.
That's going to be the derivative of the
divergence with respect to these the
probabilities in these nodes. But it
gets to be a little more complicated
than that because if you look over here,
the divergence basically is the sum is
is the uh weighted sum of the
probabilities of all the nodes at at all
the nodes within the column, right? And
so if I'm looking at the derivative of
the divergence with respect to say y 6,
I need to focus only on column 6. So I
only look for at t= 6 and everything
else goes away. And then I go down here
and I'm going to be summing down this
column and I'm going to be computing the
derivative of this guy with respect to
all of the probabilities output by the
network for the symbols out here and
those there are only three symbols B E
and for E happens to occur twice and so
when I'm computing so for the all the
symbols which are not BE or for this
term is going to be zero
for bur e and fur. If I'm looking at the
derivative for the divergence for bur,
I'm going to be looking at just the
derivative for this guy, which is gamma
6b
time log
y 6b
minus. Did this make sense over here?
Similarly, if I'm looking at the
derivative for fur, that's going to be
simply the derivative of mamma minus
gamma 6 f*
log of
y 6.
This make sense
to all of you guys? But then if I'm
looking at the derivative for y for this
symbol right for e. So the derivative of
the divergence with respect to y 6 e is
going to be the derivative of minus
gamma
6 e*
uh the gamma over here right. So gamma
* y 6 e this r is 2 I'm sorry right plus
the gamma over here - gamma like 4 e * y
6 log
y 6. I know it looks very confusing, but
did that make sense that when I'm
looking for the derivative for E, E
occurs twice in the graph and so I
actually get contributions from two
entries. Did that make sense?
Or do I need
because two and four because y occurs in
positions two and four,
right? And so here you have it.
You must compute the derivative of the
divergence with respect to all of these
elements. This is for the symbols that
are not over here. It's going to be
zero. For the rest of them, it's going
to be the sum over all nodes that
include that particular symbol
of the derivative of gamma for the node
times the log of the probability at that
node.
So given this for for bur and fur you
just get single entries for e because y4
e was copied into two locations you're
going to have to sum over both these
locations if you want to get get the
derivative of the divergence with
respect to y4 e. So again did this make
sense
all of you guys right? Yes. No. Okay.
Now let's go back with what is this
derivative? What is the derivative of
gamma tr * log y t l
that
is going to be from the laws of
differentiation
gamma * gamma divided by lo by by y plus
the derivative of gamma* log y.
Everybody good with this formula?
Yes, this first term is easy to compute.
The second term of gamma, this this
derivative turns out to be hideous
because gamma itself invokes y.
And so the second term is a bit nasty.
What do you do in engineering when you
run into a really nasty term?
Typically, what do you do when you run
into a nasty term?
break it up. How about we just ignore
it? And so we just throw it away and
come up with an alternate mathematical
explanation for it. And we say that if
you throw it away, this ends up being a
maximum likelihood estimate. Turns out
to be mathematically correct. And so
that's what it ends up being. And so the
derivative of the divergence with
respect to ytl
is simply
this uh you know for at any given node
the derivative of gamma tr log ytl with
respect to ytl simply becomes gamma
divided by y and so when you compute the
derivative of the divergence with
respect to the probability of any symbol
at any time it's simply minus1 over that
probability
times the sum of the gamas for all the
nodes at that time that include that
symbol.
This make sense
to everybody? And so here we have it,
right? We know how how exactly to
compute the derivative of the divergence
with respect to all the wires in the
network. And so here is the overall
training procedure.
You're given an input, you're given an
output sequence, you're not given an
alignment. So the first thing you do,
you set up the network, typically a
millimeter LSDN. You initialize all the
parameters of the network. Then in the
first step, you're going to pass the
input through the network and it's going
to give you a vector of output
probabilities at each time. Then from
this you construct the graph for the
reduced the reduced graph for the
compressed symbol sequence which may
include repetitions of certain symbols
and then subsequently
uh
oops
and then subsequently
on this graph you're going to perform
the forward and backward computation to
get the alphas and betas for all nodes.
From the alphas and betas you compute
the gamas and then from the gamas you
can you can compute the derivatives of
the divergence with respect to all the
probabilities
the probability vector output by the
network at each time. That derivative is
going to be zero for all the symbols
that are not in the compressed sequence.
And for the for the symbols that are in
the compressed sequence, it's just going
to be as we saw minus one over the
probability of the symbol times the sum
of all the gamas at that all the gamas
for all the nodes at that time that
include that symbol. And so we compute
the derivative of the divergence with
respect to the output of the network.
Here again I actually have the formula
over here. And then once you have the
derivative of the divergence with
respect to the output of the network,
you have the derivative of the
divergence with respect to the output of
the network at each time. You can just
use regular back propagation and
aggregate derivatives over many batches
and update parameters. Did this whole
process make sense to you guys?
Everything that we've said so far. Any
questions?
Any questions?
Okay. If it all made sense, we're good,
right? So the story story so far,
sequence tosequence models which
irregularly output symbols can be
decoded through greedy decoding which
assumes that a symbol is output at each
time and merges adjacent symbols.
They require for training they require
alignment of the output
of the output symbol sequence to the
input. This alignment is generally not
given. Training can be performed by
iteratively estimating the alignment
through WB alignment followed by times
synchronous training. Alternately, it
can be performed by optimizing the
expected divergence over all possible
alignment. This requires posterior
probabilities uh which can be computed
using the forward backward algorithm.
So
is everything clear so far? Can I
proceed? Things become faster a bit
better. Yeah.
So it's just the connection is temporal
model. The whole model is the connection
is temporal model. Okay, connection is
temporal classification.
So we got through but then we were left
with two key problems. One is a key
decoding problem. Consider the problem
where the output symbols are characters.
If I have a decode a time synchronous
greedy decode which says r e e d
is this if you compress it does it
become red or does it become read? Is
there any way of making out which of the
two it is just from this sequence?
Can you actually tell from this sequence
alone?
Yes or no? You cannot. Right?
So this is the problem we saw alluded to
earlier that if I just perform a greedy
decode and begin compressing things, we
cannot disambiguate
repetitions.
So
we have a solution. The solution is to
include an explicit extra invisible
symbol which serves to separate discrete
versions of a symbol. This is just a new
entry in the vocabulary. I'm going to
represent it by a blank. But then you
have to remember that it's actually not
seen. It's invisible. So if I get a
greedy decode which looks like this.
Three Rs, three blanks, two E's, three
blanks, and three D's. And then I
compress it by dduplication. The three
Rs become an R. The three blanks become
an invisible symbol. They're not seen
anymore. The two E become an E. The
three blanks over here become an
invisible symbol, not seen. And the 3Ds
become a D. So this becomes red. Did
this make sense that the act of
compression
compresses the invisible symbols as
well, but they cannot be seen.
Does this make sense? Yes. Similarly
over here, right? The two Rs would
compress to an R. You have a invisible
symbol. Then you have an E. Then the
three R symb blanks compress to a single
invisible symbol. The two E's compress
to a single E and the D stays a D. So
now this becomes read. Did that make
sense?
Did this make sense? Okay.
And so also over here the two Rs become
an R because you have an invisible
symbol in between the next R stays
separate you have an R then the two E
become an E then the D becomes a D
because of you have this invisible
symbol these two don't get merged the
two Ds become a D so you get two Rs an E
and two D's so using the same logic what
would this become
what would this become
R R let's see indeed you're all right
right perfect
so if I'm doing a time synchronous
decode I can get a sequence of invisible
symbols that's all I'm speaking of times
synchronous decodes over here and then
compressing them okay so here is our
fourth poll
man. It's just a a
invisible symbol is just a symbol like
an A. If you were doing a time
synchronous decode, just as you get
three E, you can get three blanks,
right?
All right, let me end this poll, guys.
And
can you tell me the answer?
This four, right?
So this is the only one that becomes
Billy because this guy is going to
become B I L Y. This is going to become
B
I L Y. This is going to become B I L Y.
This is the only one that becomes B I L
L Y. This makes sense to everybody
that when you compress it multiple
blanks just become one single invisible
symbol which is not seen. Okay.
And so here we are. Now this
introduction of the blank modifies your
forward backward algorithm. Now your
vocabulary includes the blank the
invisible symbol. And so when you pass
the input through the network, it's
going to compute the probabilities not
just for all your visible symbols, but
also the invisible symbol at each time.
And now let's say I performed a greedy
decode and picked the most likely symbol
at each time. And I got this sequence.
This is going to be two B's which
compress to a B, two E's which compress
to an E, three Fs, four Fs which
compress to a single F, and an E. I
don't have to worry about whether these
are two fs or not because I have
invisible symbol separating repetitions.
On the other hand, if I get something
like this, I have an invisible symbol at
the beginning so I won't see it. This
becomes an E. These two E compress to an
this becomes a B. These two E compressed
to an E. These two blanks will
disappear. These two Fs compress to an
F. And this becomes an E. Bye. So, did
this make sense?
Um, mana, did this answer your question?
I'm assuming it did, right? Why multiple
blanks? This is it just that that's
that's just a greedy decoding process,
right? What would this become, guys?
What would this become? Anybody? Don't
look at the answer on the slide. What is
this going to be?
there going to be two Fs because there's
a blank separating these two Fs, right?
And so you get an idea how the whole
thing works.
So this modifies our training. Now
earlier, okay, I'm changing my example
from B to ED because it gives me two D's
one after the other. If I have any if I
just compos composed a graph of this
kind and then I got an alignment when I
compress the alignment I would never get
two D's because an alignment of this
graph is going to give me something like
E D
E right and when I compress it this is
always going to give me a single D.
So this kind of graph cannot be used to
determine that I'm training for ed with
two D's and not ED with just a single D.
That make sense?
Right? But then once I introduce blanks,
things change. So here's how earlier
when you didn't have blanks, if I had
the word beefy, add B followed by E, E
followed by F followed by E.
Now
if I introduce blanks, I can have an
initial blank. It's optional, right? If
it's there, you won't see it. I need a
B. B can directly be followed by E or it
can be followed by a blank and then
followed by an E. E can. So I'm
distinguishing between what you see and
what is. And there is a money to one
mapping between what is and what you see
because the blanks are invisible and
they cannot be seen. This graph
represents all ways of getting B fe. Did
that make sense? I can have B followed
by a blank followed by an E or B just
directly followed by an E. E followed by
a blank followed by a fur or E just
directly followed by F and so on. This
make sense to everybody?
Yes. Okay. On the other hand, if I have
Eddie,
I can have an initial blank which is not
seen. I have a A can be followed by a
blank and then followed by a D or can be
directly followed by D. But
D cannot be directly followed by D
because if D were directly followed by D
any compression would compress the two
D's into a single D. So when I have two
symbols which are the same you must have
an invisible blank in the middle.
That make sense
the graph that I've got over here.
Right? And so this is how having blanks
uh makes
the mod modifies the graph. You can have
blanks everywhere because they're
invisible. You can't see them.
And they're not mandatory between two
symbols which are not the same. But if I
have two symbols which are identical
following one another, they are
mandatory between the two. Otherwise,
the two would just collapse into a
single instance. Right?
With that said, now how do I compose the
graph for training? So if I have Eddie,
this is the graph I'm going to use. A
followed by D followed by D followed by
E. But then I have blanks between every
two symbols. They are optional if the
symbols on either side are not the same.
Otherwise, they're not optional. And so
this is the this is the same graph over
here drawn vertically. That make sense
to everybody?
Do you understand what this? Okay. So if
I follow this comp create r the other
graph with what I what I'm going to call
the trellis from this this is what it
looks like the initial symbol it's
basically there's implicitly vertical
arrows going down between every two
symbols. Okay. And so this guy is just
unrolling
this graph over time. And so you have
the first at the first time I can have
either a blank or an air at the second
time. So
blank can be followed by a blank. Blank
followed can be followed by an air. A
air can be followed by an air. A can be
followed by a blank but a a air can also
be followed by a d. So I also have this
arrow.
Did this arrow make sense that this
arrow is basically reflecting
this structure?
That make sense? So also duh can only be
followed by a blank because there's only
one here. Blank can be only followed by
a duh because there's only one
connection here. that this D can be
followed either by a D or by a blank or
two because I have the skip connection
it can be followed by an E. This make
sense to everyone?
So the overall path is the first and
last columns are also allowed to end at
initial and final blanks. And everywhere
else in the graph if the symbol two
symbols away is not identical to it, you
can have a skip connection. It's a very
simple rule. If the symbol two symbols
away, so this guy and this guy are the
same symbol. So you cannot have a skip
connection. This guy and this guy are
different symbols. So you can have a
skip connection. That's it. That's the
simple rule. That make sense to
everybody
over here in the form? Okay. And now
subsequently I can use the forward
forward algorithm to compute the alphas
and betas just as before. The alphas are
still going to be following the same
rule. Alphas are zeros for all of these
guys because the graph can begin in any
one of the first two nodes. The alphas
for these two nodes are just the node
probabilities.
Then when you go through the graph as
before, the alpha for any node is the
sum of the alphas for all of its parents
times the node probability.
All nodes have at least two parents,
right? They all have at least two
parents. So if I look at this guy, this
has this has two parent, right? Let me
clear this picture. So if I look at this
guy, this has two parents. And then some
nodes
have three parents. And these are the
nodes for which the the node two nodes
away is not the same symbol. So for this
guy, this one has this one as a parent.
It has this as a parent, but it also has
this as a parent. So that's a simple
rule. Every node has itself the the
horizontal and immediately previous
connection as parents. And then if these
two symbols are if these two symbols are
not identical then the node also has the
symbol two nodes away as a parent. That
make sense for the sum of alphas?
Yes or no?
Okay. And so you sum the alphas for all
the parents and then multiply the sum of
the alphas by the node probability to
get the alpha for the node. You do this
going forward and you get the alphas for
all the nodes.
The backward algorithm is much the same.
The beta beta hats are going to be zeros
for everything but the final two nodes.
And then as you go back and the final
two nodes are simply get going to have
the node probabilities as the beta hats.
Then as you go backwards for each node
the beta hat is going to be the node
probability multiplied by the sum of the
beta hats for its children.
All nodes will have two children. But if
any node and the node two below it are
not the same symbol, then it's going to
have three children.
That make sense to everybody?
This formula over here, the beta hat is
simply the sum of the betas for all the
children times the probability. And
there's a very simple rule for
which nodes have two children and which
have three. And then of course the beta
is obtained by dividing beta hat by the
node probability.
And so here you have it. The rest of the
computation posteriors and derivatives
are computed exactly as before but using
the extended graph with blinks. So the
overall training procedure is going to
look like this. Given input and output
sequences without alignment. You want to
train models. You initialize the network
set it up typically a many many layer
LSTM. You initialize all parameters but
now you include a blank in the symbol
vocabulary.
Then in the forward pass you pass the
input through the network. We're going
to get a vector of probabilities at each
time. And then
you go through the uh entire network and
use the forward
to comput. Then uh
you go through it backwards and compute
the backward algorithm for all the nodes
and then use the alphas and betas to
compute the gamas for all the nodes. And
once you have the gamas, you can compute
the derivatives of the divergence
for this training instance with respect
to the probability vectors at each time.
And then once you have which is of
course exactly as we saw before which
was
A vector of terms where most terms are
zero. And the terms which do occur in
the symbol sequence will have
1 / the probability of the symbol times
the sum of the gamas for all nodes that
include the symbol negative.
So this divergence derivative is then
back propagated to get the diver
derivative of the divergence with
respect to the output of the network at
each time. This is further back
propagated to train the network.
So any questions?
Any questions?
No. So this overall framework we saw is
what is what is called is a connections
temporal classification
uh network model. It applies to models
that output order align but time
asynchronous outputs. The most common
uses are speech recognition and
character recognition and handwritten
character recognition, right? Or text
recognition.
So now I said that we had only partially
solved the gre the decoding problem.
That's because
the greedy decode which computes its
outputs output by finding the most
likely symbol at each time and merging
repetitions. We did solve the repetition
problem by introducing the blame, the
blank, but it's still going to be
suboptimal that finds the most likely
times synchronous output sequence, which
is not necessarily the most likely order
synchronous sequence. What do I mean by
this? Consider this. Suppose I have an
input that's six symbols long, six
inputs long. And I consider these six
alignments.
So, RR blank eed has a probability of 7.
R R blank blank ED has a probability of
68. R E E D has a probability of 69. All
three of them collapse to red. TT ED has
a probability of 71. TT blank EED has.3
and TT blank blank ED has 29. All of
these three collapse to TED. If I were
performing the the greedy decode, which
would I pick? Would I pick red or would
I pick Ted?
Which would I pick? Which of the two?
Anyone? I'm going to pick 10. This is
the highest probability, right? Which
makes more sense
just looking at these probabilities.
Different alignments of red all have
high probability. This just happens to
be some noisy outlier, right? You should
have picked red. Although just the
greedy decode ended up picking Ted. So
the greedy decode is actually
suboptimal.
A decode that considers the sum of all
alignments of the same final output
would select red
and which would be more reasonable.
Right? Remarkably greedy decoding can be
surprisingly effective when using
decoding with blanks because what
happens this is from the original paper
by Graves. When you just perform a
greedy decode, you find that the blank
ends up being the most probable symbol
most of the time and the actual symbols
begin appearing only at transition
points. And so when you collapse these
outputs, more often than not, you
actually end up getting a pretty good
decode, right? Regardless, it's
suboptimal.
So how do you make it optimal?
We want to find the most likely order
aligned symbol sequence.
What the greedy decode finds is the most
likely times synchronous symbol sequence
can be compressed. So our problem is to
find the order aligned symbol sequence
given an input that is most likely. So
we want to find the order aligned symbol
sequence which is typically shorter than
the input given the input. So to compute
the probability for this, you must sum
its probability over all possible
alignments.
How do we compute that? We already saw
this when you were looking at the
forward algorithm. When you compose this
graph, what I call the trellis,
the alpha at this bottom right node was
the sum of all possible ways of aligning
this in this symbol sequence to the
input. Do you remember that?
Yes. No. Right. So what is this alpha?
What is this alpha? It's actually the
probability of the simple sequence over
all alignments.
Right.
Yes or no?
>> Okay. And so if I want to perform
optimal decode,
what I want to do is to find the most
likely asynchronous symbol sequence,
which means that for every possible
symbol sequence, I'd have to construct
this graph and compute the alpha at this
bottom right node and then pick the
graph for which this this probability
was highest.
So that leads us to our fifth and final
poll.
actual.
Guys, can you actually mute yourself if
you're not
intending to talk to the entire class?
Okay, 10 seconds, guys.
All right.
What is the answer to the first
statement for us?
True or false?
True. Second one.
Let's see. Both are true. Right. The
actual objective of decoding is to
identify the compressed sequence that
has the highest probability given the
input. This is the same as finding the
compressed sequence with the highest
forward probability alpha for aligning
the final symbol to the the sequence to
the final and input. So you want to find
the most likely compressed sequence
given which means you want to find the
sequence s for which the alpha at the
bottom right is highest. This means you
need to explicitly compute the alpha for
every possible symbol sequence and
there's infinite of them. So the
solution that we will follow is to
organize all possible sing symbol
sequences as what I call a semi tree.
I'm going to use an example with only
two symbols S1 and S2.
There's the implicit blank symbol as
well. So the first any symbol sequence
can either begin with an S1 or begin
with an S2 or begin with a blank. So
this is a symbol sequence that is one
symbol long. This making sense that this
is a symbol sequence that's one symbol
long. It's either going to be S1 or S2
or blank S_sub_1 or blank S2 which are
just S1 and S2. Right? So now
if I want to extend this by one this S1
by another symbol, I can extend it
directly by S_2
or to extend it by S1 I have to
introduce a blank in between or I can
also have a blank followed by an S2.
This two becomes S1 S2.
Similarly, s_ub_2 can be extended
directly by s_sub_1 or blank s_sub_1 or
blank s_ub_2. So this is so this guy
over here represents subs.
This guy represents s1 s_ub_2. This guy
represents s_ub_2 s1 and this guy
represents s_ub_2 s2. This make sense to
everybody,
right? And so
I can do this. I can keep extending it
in the same manner and this represents
all possible symbol sequences in the
language which has only two symbols s1
and s_ub_2 and each node represents an
entire symbol sequence from the root to
the node. That make sense?
Yes or no?
Okay. And so this tree I'm going to lay
it out vertically. I've just redrawn the
tree as a vertical tree. So you know
blank going to S1, blank going to S2 and
so on, right? S1 goes to either blank S1
or S1 goes directly to S_UB_2. S2 goes
either to blank S1 or goes directly to
when S blank S2 or goes directly to S1.
So you get the idea, right? And then
this is time. I can unroll this tree
across time and this is going to be my
trellis.
Each row over here represents a unique
symbol sequence. So this row for example
represents the symbol sequence that ends
at s_ub_2 which is going to be if I
follow it back that's going to be s1 s2.
This row over here represents this guy
which is going to be uh let me see. Let
me follow it back. It's going to be
s2
s2. That make sense that each one of
these represents a unique symbol
sequence,
right? And now I can just use the
forward algorithm.
You know, every node in the graph
represents a unique symbol sequence. So
every row represents a unique symbol
sequence. As input comes in, I can use a
forward algorithm to keep going forward
to compute the alphas at all the nodes.
And then when I'm finally done and of
course uh at the end of in the input I
just pick the alpha which has the
highest value and the corresponding
symbol sequence is my most likely symbol
sequence. I have to make one small
modification because symbol sequences
can end either the sequence itself or
also with a blank. So I actually need to
if I want to look at the the total
probability of just the symbol sequence
S1, I have to sum the alpha for S1 as
well as alpha S1 blank, right? And so I
can compute the alphas for all the
possible symbol sequences and pick the
symbol sequence that's overall most
likely across all possible alignments.
That make sense?
Yes. No.
Right. And what would be the pro problem
with this doing this naively?
What would the problem with this be?
Well, if you can't answer me, it's going
to blow up because as you keep going
forward, the tree keeps getting larger
and larger. And so, how do we solve it?
Right? This is the theoretically correct
CTC decoder. But in practice, the graph
gets exponentially large very quickly.
To prevent this, you use pruning
strategies to keep the graph manageable.
This can cause sub-optimal decodes.
However, you know, the fact that the CTC
scores peak at symbol terminations
minimizes the damage due to pruning. So,
here's how you do it. At the first time,
you compute the alphas for all the
nodes. There's going to be a small
number of them. Then, you keep only the
top few. Say top four in my example. You
only expand the top four at the next
time. And then from those you keep only
the top four and keep going forward
until and so at each time this trellis
that you build is going to have no more
than four active nodes or whatever n
active nodes where n is the width of
your beam. And then at the final time
you're going to you're going to sum up
the alphas uh for the two you're going
to determine the most likely symbol
sequence as the symbol sequence for
which the alpha is largest. Again
keeping in mind that each symbol
sequences can be represented by up to
two alphas.
That make sense to everybody?
Yes. No.
Okay. So I have a huge pseudo code in
the slides. Uh but you're also going to
be implementing this in your homework.
So I'll skip this. Right. So the story
so far
uh sequenceto-sequence networks which
irregularly produce output symbols can
be trained by iteratively aligning the
target output to the input and times
synchronous training or optimizing the
expected error over all possible
alignments. That's CTC training.
Distinct repetition of symbols can be
disambiguated from repetitions
representing the extended output of a
symbol sequence by the introduction of
blanks. decoding can be performed by
best path decoding which is greedy
decoding or optimal CTC decoding based
on the application of the forward
algorithm to a tree structured
representation of all possible output
strengths.
So the caveat the blank structure is
only one way to deal with the problem
problem of repeating symbols. There many
variants that have been proposed uh I'll
skip this. CTC can use birectional
recurrent networks. There's nothing
stopping it. Uh or even other kinds of
models. The most common CTC applications
speech recognition speech and phone
sequence out speech speech and character
sequence out and handwriting
recognition. So,
uh, anyways,
I'll stop right here. Did the lecture
make sense to all of you guys?
Yes or no? Just give me some thumbs up.
I'd like to see 25 thumbs up. I haven't
asked for that many today yet.
Thank you. Any questions? I'll stop the
recording.